A Guide to the Virginia State Library, Office of the State Librarian, War Memorial Libraries Records, 1920-1921
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia State Library, Office of the State Librarian, War Memorial Libraries, 1920-1921
Library of Virginia
41409
.68 cubic feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Virginia State Library, date unknown.
Biographical/Historical Information
For many years, The Library of Virginia had no definitive home. Valuable early records were kept at Jamestown as early as 1676 and were then moved to the College of William and Mary for a brief period at the century's end. By 1780, extant records were moved to the Capitol in Richmond.
Coincidentally, in 1779, the Virginia General Assembly was presented among its legislation, "A Bill for Establishing a Public Library" drawn up by Thomas Jefferson. The bill provided for 2000 pounds yearly to be expended to maintain a State Library in Richmond. The facility was to be a reference library only without books being lent for home use. Perhaps ahead of its time, the bill failed to pass.
The Virginia State Library was created by an act passed by the General Assembly on January 23, 1823, to establish a public library with funds derived from the sale of William W. Hening's THE STATUTES AT LARGE. From 1823 to 1828, the Library was under the control of the governor and council. In 1828, the General Assembly created a joint committee on the library (located in a room in the southeastern corner of the Capitol) to oversee its administration. Use of the State Library was restricted to members of the state government in a policy that continued until at least 1856. The Secretary of the Commonwealth served ex officio as state librarian from 1832 to 1903.
The growth of the State Library was somewhat erratic. Book holdings increased from 1,313 in 1828 to 17,480 in 1856. Lack of funds and politics frequently intermingled to slow library development. General W.H. Richardson, State Librarian in 1852, became embroiled in an effort to remove him "to make way for some politician of democratic principles." At the close of Reconstruction, Dr. George William Bagby, then State Librarian, was terminated and his position abolished at the hands of Readjusters.
Eventually, on May 15, 1903, the General Assembly passed an act that created a library board to administer the library, authorized the deposit of public records in the library, provided for the publication of historical records by the library, and established a library fund for the purchase of books and private papers. The Library Board, which was responsible for naming the State Librarian, was itself appointed by the Board of Education. The General Assembly passed an act on March 29, 1944, transferring the power to appoint the Library Board to the governor.
While many public records somehow survived the Commonwealth's early years, many losses occurred due to fires, the ravages of war and negligence. When the library was moved, for example, in 1895 to a building separate from the Capitol, "chutes were constructed from the upper story of the Capitol to facilitate the delivery of books to the wagons of the junk dealer who had bought them." The move was poorly planned and the library's contents suffered great loss at the hands of those very authorities assigned to protect them.
The new facility quickly was found to be inadequate and efforts were made both in 1910 and 1920 to construct a proper building for the State Library and its collections. Ground was broken for the current facility on December 7, 1938. At last, on December 23, 1940, the newly completed Virginia State Library was opened to the public.
The Virginia State Library adopted the name, the Virginia State Library and Archives, in early 1987 to more adequately reflect its mission and purpose today. In July 1, 1994 the name was changed to The Library of Virginia. It serves as a general reference and research library, as the official repository of state archives and publications, and as a repository of state and federal documents. It provides assistance and advice to libraries around the state, and it administers state and federal library funds. The Archives and Records Division of the library administers the state records management program, arranges and describes records deposited in the division, and provides assistance and advice to state and local government agencies concerning the management of their records. Additionally, the agency produces many publications. The most notable among those regularly issued are the quarterly VIRGINIA CAVALCADE and the annual accession reports of the Archives and Records Division showing its most recent records and manuscript acquisitions.
Scope and Content
The War Memorial Libraries, a system throughout Virginia to "commemorate the spirit and deeds of her heroic dead in the World War" was proposed by members of the American Legion to a committee established by the General Assembly to investigate a suitable memorial to those who served and perished in World War I. There are few references to this system of libraries that was proposed, although the American Legion continued to petition the General Assembly for action on this project for several years.
The War Memorial Libraries did not come about, and more effort was spent in establishing a War Memorial Library in Richmond, as the Virginia State Library building at that time was inadequate. For more information about the War Memorial Library in Richmond, please consult the agency history for the War Memorial Commission (1920-1934).
Arrangement
Each series is arranged alphabetically.
Contents List
- I: Administrative Notes, 1920-1921
  Contains general administrative notes, including lists of contacts within localities, and correspondence extending the regrets of citizens who were not able to contribute to the development of these libraries.
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Lists of Contacts (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Regrets (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Summary by County (Box 1, Folder 3)
- II: Correspondence with citizens of localities
  Contains correspondence with contacts within many of the counties of Virginia regarding the establishment of public libraries.
  Alphabetical
  - Accomac County, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Albemarle County, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Alexandria County, 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Alleghany County, 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Amelia County, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Amherst County, 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Appomattox County, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Augusta County, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bath County, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bedford County, 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Botetourt County, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Brunswick County, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Buchanan County, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Buckingham County, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Campbell County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Caroline County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Charlotte County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Clarke County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Culpeper County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Cumberland County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Dickenson County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Dinwiddie County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Elizabeth City County 1920 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Fairfax County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Fauquier County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Franklin County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Frederick County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Giles County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Gloucester County, 1920 (Folder 2, Folder 16)
  - Goochland County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Grayson County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Greensville County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Halifax County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Hanover County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Henrico County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Henry County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Isle of Wight County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - James City County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - King William County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Lancaster County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Lee County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Loudoun County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Louisa County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Lunenburg County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Madison County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Mathews County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Mecklenburg County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Middlesex County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Montgomery County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Nansemond County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Nelson County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Norfolk County, 1920 (Folder 2, Folder 39)
  - Northampton County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Northumberland County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Nottoway County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Orange County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Page County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Patrick County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Pittsylvania County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Prince Edward County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Prince George County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Princess Anne County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Pulaski County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Richmond County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Roanoke County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Rockbridge County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Rockingham County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Shenandoah County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Southampton County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Spotsylvania County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Surry County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Sussex County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Tazewell County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Warsaw County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Warwick County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Washington County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Westmoreland County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Wise County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Wythe County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - York County, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 67)